اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
Sharhabil Bin Hasana رضي الله عنه, one of the companions, who led armies against Al-Murtaddeen(ألمرتدين)
came to the Khalifah(خليفه), Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه and he said:
O Khalifah of Rasool Ullah! Are you thinking about conquering a Ash-Sham(ألشَّام)?
Are you thinking about fighting the Romans?
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said: Yes! I am.
But I've never told anyone about my intentions.
So how did you know about it?
So Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was already thinking about attacking Ash-Sham(ألشَّام).
He was considering it.
See Ash-Sham(ألشَّام) has been in the Muslim mind since the day Rasool Allah ﷺ made the journey of Al-Isra(ألإسراء).
When Rasool Allah ﷺ went to Jerusalem and he led the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) in a Salah(صلاة).
It was symbolic of Rasool Allah ﷺ receiving the keys to the Holy Land.
Now, you are the inheritor of this blessed land.
الأَرض الَّتِي بَارَكْنَا فِيهَا
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says that, that is the blessed land, mentioned in Qur'an.
So, when Rasool Allah ﷺ goes there and leads the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) whom many of lived in the Holy Land.
The fact that Rasool Allah ﷺ is leading them
is an indication that Muhammadﷺ now is a new leader, he's the inheritor of the Haqq(حق)
and he is the carrier of the torch.
So even though the Muslims were not incharge of the holy land.
Very early on, they set their sights on Al-Ardh Al-Mubarikah(ألأرض الْمُباركة).
So Rasool Allah ﷺ before he even finishes off the effort of opening Arabia
he's sending an army to Mu'ta(مؤته), deep in the land of Ash-Sham(ألشَّام),
led by Zaid Ibn Harissa(زيد إبن حارثه).
And before that, he has sent a letter to the king of Ghassan(غسَّان),
who when he saw that Muhammadﷺ, this man from Madina is inviting him to Islam,
أسلِم تَسْلَمْ
He became very angry and arrogant, so he wanted to attack Madina.
But the Roman Emperor told him not to do so.
He's the one, who calmed him because the king of Ghassan(غسَّان) his loyalty was to the Roman emperor.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ in the ninth year, he goes out himself to the Battle of Tabook(تبوك),
which is the borderline between Hijaz(حجاز) and the Ash-Sham(ألشَّام).
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ, the following year, gives the banner to Osama Bin Zaid(أسامة بن زيد)
and he dies before Osama(أسامة) goes out, but Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) send him out.
So, the Muslims were thinking about Ash-Sham(ألشَّام) a lot, this is the land of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء),
the Muslims should inherit it.
So, Sharhabil Bin Hasana(شرحبيل بن حسنة) comes to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was thinking about this.
See there was already some things going on.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) has already sent in Khalid bin Saeed Bin Al-Aas(خالد بن سعيد بن ألعاص) to Ash-Sham(ألشَّام).
But these were small incursions, it wasn't a major campaign.
But now Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) is thinking about an all out assault
on the Roman Empire in Ash-Sham(ألشَّام) to take over the land.
It's not just merely sending in, an Army in and out.
So Sharhabil Bin Hasana(شرحبيل بن حسنة) comes to the Khalifah(خليفه) and says;
Are you thinking about fighting Ar-Rome(ألروم)?
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: Yes! How did you know?
You only asked me this question because there's a reason.
Sharhabil Bin Hasana(شرحبيل بن حسنة) said: I saw a dream.
What was a dream?
Sharhabil Bin Hasana(شرحبيل بن حسنة) said: I saw you walking among the people
and then you climbed over a very rough terrain
and you made your way up to a very high peak.
And then you and your companions took a look from that vantage point to the people under you.
And then you descended from that peak, into a very fertile plain.
A plain that is lush with vegetation, and it's full of towns and fortresses.
And then you told your companions, to wage war against the enemies of Allah
and I guarantee you victory and booty and you gave me a banner.
And I went ahead with it and I came to a town and the people offered me peace,
so I opened it peacefully and then I came back to you.
And I found you in a very great fortress sitting on a throne
and then a voice came to you and said rejoice with victory
so thank Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ and then this voice recited to you, Surah An-Nasr(سورةألنصر).
إِذَا جَاءَ نَصْرُ اللَّهِ وَالْفَتْحُ ۝
وَرَأَيْتَ النَّاسَ يَدْخُلُونَ فِي دِينِ اللَّهِ أَفْوَاجًا ۝
فَسَبِّحْ بِحَمْدِ رَبِّكَ وَاسْتَغْفِرْهُ إِنَّهُ كَانَ تَوَّابًا۝
And then I woke up, so that was the end of the dream.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) with tears swirling in his eyes.
He said: You have given me the glad tidings of opening and also my obituary.
Now Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه used to interpret dreams,
even in the presence of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Once the dream was presented to Rasool Ullah, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said;
Let me interpret it, O messenger of Allah.
He said: The interpretation of the dream is as follows.
When you saw me climbing a very rough terrain.
This means that me and my soldiers and our enemy are going to have a very rough time in this conflict.
It's going to be difficult, it's gonna be hard.
Because first you saw him among the people, all people Muslim and non Muslim.
And then Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه is now climbing this rough terrain.
So that means it's a very rough conflict.
And when you saw me at the top of the mountain,
that means in the end, we will prevail, victory will be on our side.
Because now Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is on top, along with his companions, the Muslims
and the other people are still in the foothills.
And then what was the next part of the dream?
We came down to a very fertile valley and plain,
lush with vegetation, full of fruits, many towns and fortresses.
He said and that means that after that, we will have a very comfortable living and a luxurious lifestyle.
So after this rough time, of Ghazoo(غزؤ), conquering,
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will make our life very easy, and luxurious.
Many towns, fortresses, vegetation is all under the control of Muslims,
so the Muslim lifestyle will change.
And when you saw me sitting on a throne,
this means that Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will make me rise and make the enemies of Allah, Low.
It means that Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will make me prevail over the enemies of Allah.
وَرَفَعَ أَبَوَيْهِ عَلَى الْعَرْشِ
It's an indication that Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will elevate me.
And then when you heard a voice telling me that you will be victorious,
so thank Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ and seek His forgiveness.
This means that my death is approaching
because that was the Surah(سورة) given to Rasool Allah ﷺ before he died.
إِذَا جَاءَ نَصْرُ اللَّهِ وَالْفَتْحُ ۝
وَرَأَيْتَ النَّاسَ يَدْخُلُونَ فِي دِينِ اللَّهِ أَفْوَاجًا ۝
فَسَبِّحْ بِحَمْدِ رَبِّكَ وَاسْتَغْفِرْهُ إِنَّهُ كَانَ تَوَّابًا۝
So that means, this is my death and then with tears flowing down his cheeks.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said: In the Name of Allah,
I'm going to enjoin good and forbid evil.
And I'm going to mobilize and prepare the soldiers to the enemies of Allah
in the east and the west, of the Earth,
until they say that Allah is One with no associates or until they pay me the Jizya(جزية)
and they are humiliated.
This is the command of Allah and this is the Sunnah(سنة) of Rasool Ullah.
So when Allah takes away my soul, He would not find me weak or incapable
and He will find me searching for the rewards of Al-Mujahideen(مجاهدين).
So Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه has now made up his mind
that they will start the Ghazoo(غزؤ) of Ar-Rome(ألروم).
So, he calls the Sahabah(صحابه) to an assembly to meet
and he will present them with his idea, Shura(شورى).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه, he invites, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب),
Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان), Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب),
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف), Saad Ib Abi Waqas(سعدإبن أبي وقاص),
Talha Bin Ubaid-Illah(طلحة بن عبيدالله), Az-Zubair Bin Awwam(ألزبير بن عوام)
along with the leaders of Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) and Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار).
And then Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه after praising Allah, He says that
I am thinking about conquering Ash-Sham(ألشَّام), and fighting Ar-Rome(ألروم).
So, that if someone dies, they die as a Shaheed(شَهِيد)
and if they live, they live with victory and Ghanimah(غنيمه), booty.
So what do you think?
He is now seeking their advice.
فَليُشِّرَ عَلَيَّ كُلُّ امْراٍ بمَبلَغ رَائ
Give me your opinion? Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه was the first to speak.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: He first of all said, after praising Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ,
he said: Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ gives His blessing to whomever He wishes.
I have been thinking about this and I wanted to present the idea to you
but here you are doing it before me.
Because whenever we and you, race in anything good you always come out first.
And this is the favor of Allah that He gives to whomever He wishes.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) is saying: I was thinking about the same thing.
So this shows you that the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم
were thinking seriously about the issue of Ash-Sham(ألشَّام)
and how to deal with it, and it has occupied their minds.
So Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: I was thinking about this
and I never got around to doing it until
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ destined that you would be the first one to mention.
He said: My view is,
you send an army after an army into their land.
The exact words,
سَرِّبْ اِلَيْهِمْ بالْخيل في إثر الخيل وبعث الرجال تتبعو الرجال والجنود تتلوه الجنود
Send in cavalries, following cavalries and infantries, following infantries,
and armies following armies.
What Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) means by that,
is that you sent in the armies in batches, in pieces, one army after another
and these armies attack from different directions and get into the land of Ar-Rome(ألروم).
That was the view of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه.
فان الله عزوجل ناصرٌ الدين ومعز الإسلام واهل
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will give victory to His religion, and Allah will honor Islam.
So this was the view of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف), he stood up and said;
I disagree with what Umar(عُمَر) said.
This is Ar-Rome(ألروم), Wa Banul Asfar(وبنوالأصفر),
Banul Asfar(بنوالأصفر) is the name the Arab used to give to the white, the European.
They wouldn't call them white, they would say the yellow, Banul Asfar(بنوالأصفر).
So the Romans are the sons of Al-Asfar(ألاصفر).
حدٌ حديد ورُكنٌ الشديد
They have a strong back.
So Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) was saying
that this is not an issue to be taken lightly, this is Ar-Rome(ألروم)
and they have a very vast land and a lot of enforcements
and whenever we get into their land,
they will have an ocean of people behind that, to support them in their conflict with us.
And that's a true characteristic of Ar-Rome(ألروم).
It's an entire continent, and they were ruling in addition to the continent of Europe,
they're ruling over North Africa, Egypt and Ash-Sham(ألشَّام).
So Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) was telling the Khalifah(خليفه) that
this is not a regular foe, this is Ar-Rome(أللروم)!
So he said: My view is to deal with the issue as following,
والله ما أرى أن تقحم الخيل عليهم إقحامًا، ولكن تبعث الخيل،
فتغير في أداني أرضهم، ثم تبعثها فتغير، ثم ترجع إليك
فإذا فعلوا ذلك مرارًا أضروا بعدوهم، وغنموا من أداني أرضهم،
فقووا بذلك على قتالهم
My view is that you send in bands, of horsemen to raid their land
and you raid the remote areas of their empire.
So rather than sending conventional armies, you follow the way of raids
small bands that would go in raid capture booty and come back.
Now Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) was saying two things:
First of all, you weaken them by doing that, so you always keep them on alert.
And you always keep on hitting their defenses without giving them a chance to hit you back.
And then what Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) said and you can see
that Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) is thinking, his mind was functioning in the business way.
Yani(يعني) Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) was a businessman.
So he's thinking about how to finance this campaign.
He's saying these raids in addition to weakening the enemy and keeping them always on the defensive,
through that booty, you would finance the campaign.
So, the treasury of the Islamic Khilafah(خِلَافَه) wouldn't have to pay for it.
So rather than pay for it from Madina, you have them pay for their own campaign.
And then when you are satisfied that's about time to make your move against them.
Then what I want you to do or what I suggest you to do is that you send out messengers,
to recruit the people of Yemen, from every corner
and the people of Rabiya(ربيعة) and the people Mudhar(مضر).
And then you lead the army yourself or you appoint somebody to lead it in your place
and In sha Allah(إن شاء الله), Allah will give you victory.
The opinion of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was an opinion,
you can see the influence of the personality in the opinion.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) wanted an all out assault,
send out the armies, let them fight them from every direction, until you take over the land.
While Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) wanted to test the waters first.
Go in send small bands, raid them, get booty.
When you feel that you're ready to make your move and you you've tested the waters enough.
Then you mobilize a huge army to do the effort for you.
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) wants the Khalifah(خليفه) to invest a little bit in the beginning.
If it's a profitable business, then put your money in it, but don't jump in it at once.
Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان) then gave his opinion, he said;
O Khalifah(خليفه) of the Messenger of Allah,
Your opinion is blessed, so whatever you see befitting
go ahead with it and we will follow through.
Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان) is saying that we trust your opinion.
We trust your view, we trust your wisdom, you make the decision, and we'll follow you.
Talha(طلحة), Zubair(زبير) and other Sahabah(صحابه) said the same thing.
And Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) is quiet.
So, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: We didn't hear from you, Ali(علي), how come you are quiet?
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) said;
I think that you are a blessed person and you carry good omen
and if you lead the army yourself or you appoint somebody in your place to do it,
you will be victorious.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said: How wonderful these words are.
How do you know?
Why did you make the judgment that I will win?
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) said: I've heard Rasool Allah ﷺ say;
لا يزال الدين ظاهرًا على كل من ناوأه، حتى يقوم الدين وأهله ظاهرين
I've heard Rasool Allah ﷺ say that this religion will prevail against all the enemies
until it stands up firm with the Muslims prevailing.
This is a promise from Rasool Allah ﷺ it will happen.
And this is the positiveness that the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم had
even before the battle they already knew the outcome, we're gonna win.
It doesn't make a difference whether you led it
or you appointed somebody in your place to lead it, which way you follow,
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will give us victory.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was very happy to hear these words and he made up his mind
and it was a mixture of both the opinion of Umar(عُمَر)
and the opinion of Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف).
What Abu Bakr رضي الله عنه did?
Is that he sent out four armies and that's the part of the opinion of Umar(عُمَر) that he adopted.
And then he followed the second part of the advice of Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن),
and that is to mobilize people from every corner and bring them ahead to fight in this war.
So he's bringing people, who are very far away from the battlefield,
which means that there's an additional effort on their behalf.
Because bringing the people of Rabiyah(ربيعة) from Iraq
and the people of Yemen, from Al-Yemen(أليمن) and taking them all the way to Ash-Sham(ألشَّام)
is an additional effort.
But since this is a confrontation with the superpower of the time,
and it is to wrestle their control over the holy land which they view as the Heartland,
this is not going to be an easy affair and therefore it needs some special recruitment effort.
So Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه send Anas Ibn Malik(أنس إبن مالك) with a letter to Yemen.
This letter states,
In the Name of Allah, the all Compassionate, the Merciful,
from the successor of the Messenger of Allah, to whomever this message is read to,
from the believers and the Muslims of the people of Yemen.
(سلامٌ عليكم).
Allah has prescribed Jihad(جهاد) on the believers
and commanded them to set out light and heavy.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى said fight in the path of Allah with your wealth and yourselves.
Jihad(جهاد) is a mandate and its reward from Allah is great.
We have assembled the Muslims in our area for Jihad(جهاد) against the Romans in Ash-Sham(ألشَّام)
and they hasten towards that.
Their armies have already set out, so hasten towards, what they have hasten towards,
you would then get one of the best two, either martyrdom, or victory and booty.
Allah is not pleased by words alone without deeds.
So Jihad(جهاد) must continue until they follow the religion of truth and accept the governance of the book of Allah.
May Allah protect your religion, guide your hearts, purify your deeds,
and grant you the reward of the Mujahideen(مجاهدين).
In this letter, Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) is telling the people the objectives
of fighting in the sake of Allah, which are two.
Number one;
that this is part of the Ibadah(عبادة) regardless, it is part of the Ibadah(عبادة).
He said that Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ does not accept words without deeds.
So for your words, to be true,
they must be accompanied by Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
The second objective is that people either become Muslim or they give the Jizya(جزية)
and they accept the rule of the book of Allah because by giving Jizya(جزية),
they have accepted the Hukum(حكم) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ in Qur'an
because Jizya(جزية) is a Quranic command.
So these are the two objectives of fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
Anas Ibn Malik(أنس إبن مالك) would go and read this letter to the people in every town.
Anas Ibn Malik(أنس إبن مالك) came back to Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
giving him the good news, he said;
أبشر قد عطوك شعثًا غبرا
ابطال اليمن وشجعانها وفرسانها
وقد سارو اليك بضرار والحرم والأموال
He said: Rejoice! They have came to you covered in dust,
the heroes of Yemen and the brave men among them and their knights.
They came to you along with their children, their wives and their wealth.
So this is a campaign that demands them to move out of their land
because of the huge distance so they are moving out
with their wealth and with their families, going Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
So this is the level of sacrifice that was demanded in those days.
One of the kings of Yemen, his name is Zulkulaa Al-Himyari(ذوالكلاع ألحميري).
He came into Madina, five days after Anas Ibn Malik(أنس إبن مالك) arrived, immediate response.
Came in with a few 100 of his followers.
He came in, wearing a crown all of these jewels in it and dressed in a robe with gold, very extravagant.
He's a King, comes into Madina and he sees the Khalifah(خليفه) Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
wrapped in very mediocre and normal pieces of cloth,
without any bodyguards, living in a mud house.
That sight of the Khalifah(خليفه) of the Muslims affected this man so much.
He took off all of those expensive clothes, went to the market of Madina
where all what you would find is very rough fabrics.
He bought himself some of that and he put it on.
His people told him you're gonna embarrass us in front of Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) Wal-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار),
he said that's it, that's what that way is over.
And now we're gonna follow the way of Zuhd(زهد), austerity.
When people see a role model in front of them, it is more powerful than words
you could have spoken to Zulkulaa Al-Himyari(ذوالكلاع ألحميري) about Zuhd(زهد) in a theoretical way,
it wouldn't have that impact on him.
That the sight of the Khalifah(خليفه) Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) had.
Also people usually follow the person, who's in power, and the nation who's in power
people usually follow the role model of the powerful nations,
their way becomes the adopted way.
So people listen to their songs, watch their movies, wear their clothes,
and that is something that Ibn Khaldoon(إبن خلدون) said, is a human trait
the weak follows the strong.
Zulkulaa Al-Himyari(ذوالكلاع ألحميري) who's a king, but he's under the Khilafah(خِلَافَه) now.
When he sees that the Khalifah(خليفه) doesn't mind wearing very cheap clothes, rough fabrics.
He was willing to take off all of that extravagant luxurious clothes that he had on,
because now their role model was Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
So the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم were setting new standards
and they were giving the people a new example.
So without them speaking, they would go into these territories
because they opened them with Izzah(عزة).
See they didn't go into make Da'wah(دعوة) in a very humiliating way.
They didn't go begging the people to become Muslim
and compromising in the religion, they went in with Izzah(عزة).
They went in with armies, and they conquered the lands of people.
And then they would go to the Masjid(مسجد) and the people would come to them to learn from them.
Because they would see them as the people, whom the example of, should be followed.
So the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم without speaking, people would adopt their ways.
And with little effort, entire tribes will enter into the fold of Islam.
So the method of Da'wah(دعوة) of the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم
was a way where they would present Islam in a very honorable way, with Izzah(عزة).
So now, Al-Khalifah رضي الله عنه set the armies, four armies.
First Army was the army of Yazeed Bin Abi Sufiyan(يزيد بن أبي سفيان).
He appointed him over 7000 soldiers and his destination was Dimashq(دمشق), Damascus.
Second Army under the leadership of Sharhabil Bin Hasana(شرحبيل بن حسنة)
with 3000 Soldiers, his destination is Tabook(تبوك)
and to protect the rear of the Muslims
and to be a reinforcement for them because the Tabook(تبوك) is the closest towards Al-Madina.
Third Army 3000 led by Abu Obaidah Amr Bin Jarrah(ابوعبيدة عمرو بن جراح)
and his destination is Hims(حمص) in Syria.
The Fourth Army of 7000, led by Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص)
and his destination was Falastine(فلسطين) and he sent them out.
Al-Khalifah(ألخليفه) would walk with every one of these leaders,
while they are riding their horses and the Khalifah(خليفه) is walking
and he would give them a Naseeha(نصيحة), give every one of them an advice.
I'll read to you the advice that he gave to Yazeed Ibn Abi Sufiyan(يزيد إبن أبي سفيان)
which was the first army to march, to set out.
He said: I am appointing you to lead this army to test you and to try you.
If you perform well, I will give you more.
And if you don't, I will change you.
So I advise you to have Taqwa(تقوى) of Allah
because he can see your inside just as he can see your outside.
I'm appointing you into the post of Khalid Bin Saeed Bin Aas(خالد بن سعيد بن ألعاص).
Stay away from the arrogance and tribalism of Jahiliyyah(جَاهلِيَّة),
when you join your soldiers, be a good companion of them.
And if you deliver a speech to them, then be brief, otherwise they will forget the message.
Improve the state of yourself, the state of your soldiers will improve.
Pray Salah(صلاة) at the appointed time
and complete your Sujood(سجود) and Rukooh(ركوع) and have Khushoo(خشوع) in Salah(صلاة).
When you receive envoys from your enemy, be kind with them and generous,
but do not allow them extended stay, otherwise they will learn of your weaknesses.
Have them stay among your strongest forces and allow no one but yourself to speak to them.
When you seek counsel, be straightforward and truthful,
in order to receive the best advice.
Spend time at night chatting with your soldiers,
then you will receive news and veils will be lifted,
spread out your guards and pay them unannounced visits
and whenever you see any carelessness in guarding your army, then punish them moderately.
Do not spend time with people, who waste their time,
but spend it with the people of truth and loyalty.
Beware of financial abuse because it draws poverty closer and victory further.
You will find men devoted to worship in monasteries, leave them alone.
This is a wonderful advice that Al-Khalifah(ألخليفه) gave to Yazeed(يزيد),
we want to take a look at some of the lessons to be learned from it.
Number one, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) saying that
being a leader you're going to be held accountable for what you're doing.
He said: I put you in this position to try you.
This is the first time he's appointed Yazeed(يزيد) to a position of leadership. He said:
I'm putting you in this position to test you and try you.
If you perform well, I'll give you more.
If not I will change you, this is not for life.
When the leader feels that their appointment is for life, they would slack,
so Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is saying you could be changed depending on how you conduct yourself
and you are going to be held accountable for everything that you do.
Number two, the Taqwa(تقوى) of Allah.
This is the most important Naseeha(نصيحة) to fear Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Number three, he is warning him the perils of nationalism and tribalism.
Now Yazeed Ibn Abi Sufiyan(يزيد إبن أبي سفيان) comes from a very prominent family in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
his father Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) was the leader of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
and he's the one, who led the war against Muhammadﷺ for the major part of his life.
But then Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) became Muslim when Makkah was opened.
So Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is now appointing his son Yazeed(يزيد) to lead an army.
So he's warning him from any remnants of Jahiliyyah(جَاهلِيَّة) that might still be in the heart of the new Muslim.
Stay away from tribalism and nationalism!
Now it's the brotherhood of Islam.
He said: Be brief.
When you speak to your soldiers, don't give them long reminders and this is a Naseeha(نصيحة)
that should to be given to every speaker, don't give their long reminders because,
يُنسي آخرالكلام أوَّلًا
The latter part will make you forget the former.
So be brief, especially when you're delivering to them instructions of battle,
Be very brief if you want your words to be remembered, and then he said;
Take care of yourself first.
As the Khalifah(خليفه) he is teaching the leaders that if you want your soldiers to improve,
then you need to improve yourself.
If you have Taqwa(تقوى), they will have Taqwa(تقوى),
if you take care of the commands of Allah, they will take care of the commands of Allah
if you observe the orders of Allah, they will observe them too.
So when the leader improves himself, that improvement is actually an investment for the people
it will improve them too.
You can't expect the people to be truthful when you're not.
You can't expect them to be honest, when you're not honest with them.
You can't expect them to sacrifice when the leader is not sacrificing.
But when the people see all of these virtues in the leader
that will encourage them to do the same.
Number six, the importance of Salah(صلاة).
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is sending out an army to fight an enemy.
You couldn't be busy with preparing the logistics of the army
that did not make him forget Salah(صلاة).
In fact, he would not forget Salah(صلاة) and he would insist on the importance of it
because he knows that victory comes through our Ibadah(عبادة).
So he's telling him that you need to pray Salah(صلاة) on time.
The Rukoo(ركوع) and Sujood(سجود) needs to be complete.
Because in army you're moving from one place to another you're busy.
You're in a state of fear, that's not an excuse to make you pray the Salah(صلاة) without Khushoo(خشوع).
You still have to have Khushoo(خشوع) in your Salah(صلاة),
even though there are as many distractions, as there could be,
there is no situation with more distractions
than an army fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
Nevertheless, you still have to have Khushoo(خشوع)
and Rukoo(ركوع) and Sujood(سجود) need to be complete.
What about the people who are living in the luxury with no problems whatsoever,
no distractions whatsoever, and their Salah(صلاة) is like an exercise, pushups.
Number seven, kindness and care towards the envoys of the enemy.
He said: When you receive messengers, or envoys or delegations coming from the enemy,
be kind with them even though they are your enemy, but Be kind.
Be generous with them when they come and don't allow them to stay for too long,
generous is something, kind is something
and allowing them free access to your army is something else.
So kindness is not being naive.
So he said: Don't allow them to stay for so long.
And then he told him and have them stay among the strongest and more powerful forces that you have.
So, that they get an impression of your strength and not your weakness.
And then he said: Don't allow anybody speak to them.
You alone should speak to these envoys.
Number eight, Shura(شورى) only works with honesty and truth.
When you are seeking Shura(شورى) from your council of generals or leaders of the army.
You have to give them a complete picture of what is happening,
if you want to get the right advice
you can't give them some information and withhold some
and then think that you're going to get the right Naseeha(نصيحة).
If you are asking for Shura(شورى).
The person who's giving you Shura(شورى) must have all of the variables
in order to make a judgment and give you the right Naseeha(نصيحة).
Because you might say well, Allah سبحانه وتعالى has said that if you make Shura(شورى),
your decision will be right and I made Shura(شورى) and it didn't turn out to be right.
That's because he didn't tell the people the entire story.
So Naseeha(نصيحة) needs to be done in the right way, if you want the fruits of Naseeha(نصيحة).
Number nine, intermingling with the soldiers, you should not be aloof from the soldiers.
He said: Go and chat with them at night.
And night time is the time, when you would get the information and the news
because that's when the Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) there's something about talking at night.
The resistance is less, so a person is more willing to speak about private things or secrets
that otherwise they wouldn't be willing to speak about during daytime
if you want to discover something investigate it at night.
Something about the moonlight and the stars
romantic settings that makes a person very open in their talk.
The Sahabah رضي الله عنهم had Hikmah(حكمة) and wisdom they knew how to get things done.
So he said: Go and chat with your soldiers at night, the veils will be lifted.
You'll get to know the reality of the condition of your soldiers.
That's how you will have access to information and news.
Go around! Spend time with them! Talk!
Number Ten, guarding the Muslim army.
He said: Appoint guards and then pay them unannounced visits.
And if you see any flaws, any mistakes then you need to punish them for it,
but punish them for it modestly.
Don't be extreme.
Don't give them free go at everything but at the same time don't be very strict.
Number 11, the importance of good company.
Don't spend your time with people, who waste their time.
You need to be serious surround yourself with the people of As-Sidq(ألصدق),
the people of Al-Haq(ألحق), the people have the truth
and Ahlul Wafaa(أهل الوفاء), the people who are grateful.
You want to have grateful people around you, people who will help you,
when you're in need, people who will not betray you in times of difficulty.
Because there are some people who are very good in amusing.
They could make a very good company to amuse you.
But when things get serious, they're gonna flee from around you.
So he said: Have the people of Wafa(وفا) around you.
As a soldier, you want to have loyal people around you.
So he is saying to the leader of the Army, have these as your close associates.
Number 12, the handling of money.
He said: If there is financial abuse in the army, Ghalool(غلول).
This would make poverty closer to you and victory further away.
When Sharhabil Bin Hasana(شرحبيل بن حسنة) was setting out the Khalifah(خليفه) accompanied him
and then he asked him, he said: Did you hear my instructions to Yazeed(يزيد)?
He said: Yes! He said: Follow them.
And there are a few more points which I forgot to mention to him
and I will mention them to you.
He said: Be patient when you meet your enemy.
Patience is the key.
صْبِرُواْ وَصَابِرُواْ وَرَابِطُواْ
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says: Isbiroo(إصبرو) be patient, Wasabiroo(وصابرو),
Wasabiroo(وصابرو) means is that you outdo the enemy in patience.
So you could be patient, but the enemy could be more patient than you.
I mean, you could be following the first part of the Ayah(آية) which is, Isbiroo(إصبرو), Be patient.
But what if your enemy is also patient, What do you do? Sabiro(صابرو)
which means you compete with them in the degree of patience, until you outdo them in that.
And there's a story about Antara(أنترى), who's like a legendary figure in courage and bravery.
Antara(أنترى) was asked by someone how come you always win against your enemy?
What makes you always victorious?
He said: I'll tell you, why? You stick your finger in my mouth.
And I'll stick my finger in yours and then we'll both bite.
He said: Alright! Let's try this and he put his finger
so Antara(عنترى) started biting his finger and the other guy is biting Antara(عنترى)'s finger
and they're crushing each others finger.
So the man after a while, he screams and said: I give up.
Antara(عنترى) said;
If you would have waited for just one more moment, I would have given up
and that's why I always win against my enemy.
So it's that one moment that you are willing to wait
to outdo the enemy in patients that makes it or breaks it.
Second Naseeha(نَصيحة), visit the sick and the injured and attend the Janazah(جنازة),
the leader must be part of the people.
When a soldier is injured, visit them.
When a soldier is sick visit them, when there is a Janazah(جناز), attend the Janazah(جنازة).
Don't be separate from the people, don't make a barrier between you and them.
And then he said: Remember Allah a lot,
وَذْكُرالله كَثِيْرَا
"Remember Allah a lot. "
So, these are his words of advice that he gave to Sharhabil Bin Hasana(شرحبيل بن حسنة).
He also gives them a words to Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص), but before.
With Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص), Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) was appointed to Oman(عمان).
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) was appointed by Rasool Allah ﷺ to be the governor of Oman(عمان).
When the Riddah(ردَّة) happened.
He had to move out - but then Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) sent him a letter saying;
I have restored you to the office to which the Messenger of Allah appointed you,
meaning Oman(عمان).
I would like Abu Abdullah(أبوعبدالله) to devote you entirely
to that which is better for you in your present life and in the hereafter,
unless that which you have now is preferable to you.
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is saying,
Rasool Ullah appointed you to Oman(عمان), I will appoint you to the same post.
However, I have something which is better for you in this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا)
and better for you in Aakhira(آخرة).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) did not want to change the post of anyone, who was appointed by Rasool Allah ﷺ,
unless he's going to give him something better.
He never ever fired anybody who was appointed by Rasool Ullah.
So, since Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) was appointed by Rasool Ullah, to govern Oman(عمان),
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: I'm giving you that appointment again.
However, there's something better I'm going to leave the choice to you.
And what Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) had in mind is the opening of Falastine(فلسطين),
which was better for Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا)
because it's the position of Jihad(جهاد) first of all, and it's better for him in Akhirah(آخرة).
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) sent a letter back he said: I am one of the arrows of Islam
and you after Allah are the one, who shoots them and collect them.
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) is saying: I'm an arrow that belongs to Islam,
and you are the archer.
Look for the strongest, most fearsome and best of them and aim me at it
and I will be your soldier.
I am an arrow you point it to whichever direction you want and aim me
So Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) immediately called him to come, summoned him to come to Madina,
and he appointed him to lead the army that's going to Falastine(فلسطين).
Now, the four armies took separate routes into Ash-Sham(ألشَّام)
and Heracul(هراقل) sensing the danger has set base in Antaqia(أنتاكية), Antioch.
And he in turn, arranged his armies
and he sent out four armies to descend on the four armies of the Sahabah(صحابه).
The first army led by his brother, Theodore
90,000 soldiers, and they are to meet Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص).
Now Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) how many did he have?
7000,
7000 against 90,000.
George the son of Theodore is to meet with Yazeed(يزيد), it doesn't mention the numbers.
Darqus to Sharhabil(شرحبيل) also doesn't mention the numbers
and Qabqar in Latin, it's Visorious it's 60,000 to meet Abu Obaidah Amr Bin Jarrah(أبوعبيدةعمروبن جرَّاح).
So these are huge armies.
Now, when the Sahabah(صحابه) the leaders of the four armies saw the numbers that they are facing,
they started sending letters to the Khalifah(خليفه), help us.
Abu Obaidah(أبوعبيدة) sent a letter. Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) sent a letter.
Yazeed(يزيد) they're all asking for help.
Allah Ho Alam(ألله أغلم) maybe they didn't expect such numbers or what?
But Al-Khalifah(ألخليفه) was starting to get all of these S.O.S. messages from the generals in the field.
Abu Obaidah(أبوعبيدة) he sent a letter, he said:
In the Name of Allah, the all Compassionate, the Merciful.
To the servant of Allah Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), the successor of the messenger of Allah ﷺ
from Abu Obaidah Amr Bin Jarrah(أبوعبيدةعمروبن جرَّاح)
(السلام عليكم)
I praise Allah and I ask Allah to honor Islam and his followers and to grant them victory.
I have received news that Heraclius the king of the Romans
has set base in a town in Ash-Sham(ألشَّام) called; Antioch
and that he sent out to his people, the people of his kingdom and He mobilized them.
They responded to his call in great numbers.
I wanted to inform you of this to give us your opinion.
والسلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته
The two key things in this letter is number one, that Heraclius is in Antioch.
So he telling the Khalifah(خليفه) that Heracul(هراقل) is taking this so serious,
he moved out of his capital, Constantinople, and he came to Antioch to be close to the field of operations.
So the Romans are taking this very seriously.
The second thing, is that he sent out to the people of his kingdom, calling them and he said:
فجاعه على صعب والذلول
Meaning they flooded from every direction, huge numbers started descending on us.
So these are the two things in the letter.
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), he sent a letter back,
he said: In the Name of Allah, the Compassionate, the Merciful.
I received your letter about what Heraclius the king of the Romans has done.
In regards to his establishing, setting base in Antioch,
It is his defeat and your victory.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه is a leader, who has confidence in the victory of Allah.
And he wants to emanate that confidence
he wants that confidence to get into the hearts of a Sahabah رضي الله عنهم who are leading these battles.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه is in charge of a very, very difficult campaign.
First of all, because it's not the only thing he's doing.
He is running two separate campaigns, one against the Persian Empire in Iraq,
and the second one against the Romans in Ash-Sham(ألشَّام).
So he's having to deal with two different fronts in the same time.
Number two, he's running very, very low in terms of resources.
He doesn't have any more people(men), and in terms of the finances, the Treasury is bankrupt.
So the situation is very difficult on Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
And this is a situation where only a very, very strong hearted leader could deal with.
First of all, this is a voluntary thing, he didn't have to send these armies.
The Romans were not an eminent threat, on Madina, he could have waited,
but Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه does not want a moment to pass
without him spreading the message of Allah and we read
his instructions to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) in our previous session.
He is telling Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) and look at what I have done
the exact day the Messenger of Allah has passed away.
Meaning don't let any catastrophe divert you from what Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has appointed you to,
even though the Messenger of Allah has died, and that's the greatest disaster to befall us.
I would still working on the issue of Khilafah(خِلَافَه).
Three days later, I'm sending out the army of Osama(أسامة).
So, he is telling Umar(عُمَر) don't let a moment pass you by without fulfilling your role in Da'wah(دعوة) and Jihad(جهاد).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه wants to give good hope and confidence
to Abu Obaidah Amr Bin Jarrah(أبوعبيدةعمروبن جرَّاح) and the other Sahabah رضي الله عنهم.
So, he tells him: When you say that Heracul(هراقل) is an Antakiya(أنتاكية)
that's good news for you that he is going to be defeated and you will be victorious.
If he is taking it so seriously, that means that he's afraid and this is for our benefit.
So that's not something to terrify me with.
That's, in fact, good news, in my view, it also shows you the positiveness of the Sahabah(صحابه).
Something that will be taken by others as an evil omen,
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه sees it as Fa'al Al-Hasan(فعل الحسن), it's good news.
And then, regarding what you mentioned about the Romans assembling for you,
the people of their empire and massing for you, huge armies
is something that we, and you already knew would happen.
So Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is trying to tell him, what's the news in that?
He didn't tell me anything new. We and you,
قد كنَّا نحن أنتم تعلمون أنَّه حاصل
We and you, already knew that this is expected and this would happen and then he said;
A people would not give up their reign and leave their kingdom without the fight.
Do you think that the Romans just walk out and give you Ash-Sham(ألشَّام)?
What do you expect, they're gonna fight you with one or two soldiers.?
It only makes sense that they will do this and even more.
So he said: You're not telling me anything new.
You should have already known better that they will do their best to fight you.
Because people are not going to give up their reign
and walk out of the kingdom without fighting, this is something expected
and it's the price you have to pay for Jihad(جهاد) and Da'wah(دعوة) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله عزوجل).
And then he told him: And you know that attacking them are men, who love death,
just as they love life,
and they love Jihad(جهاد) more than they love virgin woman and wealth.
One man of these is stronger than 1000 of the enemy.
So face your enemy with your soldiers,
and do not feel in need of Muslims who are not with you, because Allah is with you.
He is telling him: Don't ask me for any reinforcements.
Don't expect any Muslims, who are not with you to join you, because Allah is with you.
Don't look forward for that to happen.
So he's establishing the Aqeedah(عقيدة) in the hearts of Abu Obaidah(أبوعبيدة).
That Allah is with you and you don't need anybody else.
But then he turns around and he says;
Nevertheless, I will still reinforce you until you're satisfied.
Don't expect it. Don't look forward to it. Put your trust in Allah.
Nevertheless, I'm going to send you a reinforcement until I make you happy.
Obviously, when Abu Obaidah(أبوعبيدة) reads such a letter to the Muslim soldiers,
this is good news for them, this will uplift their spirits.
Numbers, not a problem, one of us is equal 1000.
Heracul(هراقل) in in Antakiya(أنتاكية),
we should take that as good news that that's the end of his kingdom.
It also shows you that the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم did not expect people with especially the Romans,
the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم knew that they're not just give up and hand over the land to you,
without fighting and Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) in his advice he said;
حدٌ حديد ورُكنٌ الشديد
So they had a very practical view of life
and how people are going to receive the Da'wah(دعوة) of Islam.
Now, the four armies are in dilemma, the numbers are huge,
and even though Al-Khalifah(خليفه) is giving them this boost,
and he sent a letter to Yazeed(يزيد) for example, we just briefly go through the letter that he sent to your Yazeed(يزيد).
He said: Alhamdulillah(ألحمدلله)  Allah! has given us victory in the time of Rasool Ullah
through putting fear in the hearts of the enemy,
and He assisted us with angels and the One, Who assists us with angels
and assisted us with putting fear in the hearts of the enemy is our Lord today.
And we're fighting for the same purpose.
Allah, Who assisted us yesterday is our Lord today and He will assist us today and tomorrow.
He's telling Yazeed(يزيد) about things that Yazeed(يزيد) did not witness.
Yazeed(يزيد) was a late Muslim. He did not attend Badr(بدر) on the side of the Muslims.
So Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was telling him, in those days we didn't have numbers
but Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has still given us victory.
So don't worry about the numbers that you're mentioning to me.
And then he said: And the ones, who bear witness that Allah is One
are not like the ones, who associate other gods with Allah.
And then he said that a small group can gain victory over a large group,
if they have Taqwa(تقوى) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, and then he also told him in the end,
and I will assist you with some reinforcements,
and then he responded to the letter of Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص).
He said: You telling me that the Romans have gathered to you and assembled large armies,
but Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has never given us victory, during the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ through numbers.
We used to fight with Rasool Allah ﷺ and we only had two horses
and we used to take turns on riding our camels.
In the battle of Uhud(أحَد), we only had one horse.
Rasool Allah ﷺ would ride it and then he would give it to some of us.
And then he told Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) that you and your army should stay away from sins.
So these were the Naseeha(نَصيحة) of Al-Khalifah(خليفه).
Now, what's the plan?
What was the plan of Al-Khalifah(خليفه), how to deal with this situation?
Things are now different.
The armies are faced with a huge opponent.
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) even though he told his commanders in the field to seek no assistance from anyone but Allah
and don't expect reinforcements.
He feels that there is still a need to reinforce these armies.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) realizes that, but he has no other soldiers.
He has squeezed Yemen and brought out the tribes of Himyar(حمير)
and Kinda(كندة) and Hazara Moat(حضرالموت) and they're all set out.
Where else can he get soldiers from?
The only thing he could come up with, is to ask Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
to split up the arm in Iraq and set out to reinforce the Muslims in Ash-Sham(ألشَّام).
That's the only thing he could do.
That's the only resource, he has left.
Obviously, by doing that he would weaken the Muslims in Iraq,
because he will only leave behind half of the forces.
But he felt that that's a temporary sacrifice that he could afford.
And he wanted the this army to go to Ash-Sham(ألشَّام) finish off the job in Ash-Sham(ألشَّام)
and to immediately return to Iraq, where they belong.
And we talked about this splitting of the army in the last session
between Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) and Al-Muthanna Bin Harissa(ألمثنى بن حارثه)
but we didn't talk about how Khalid(خالد) got from Iraq to Ash-Sham(ألشَّام).
Khalid Ibn Walid رضي الله عنه received this letter from the Khalifah(خليفه)
telling him, immediately to go and rescue the Muslims of Ash-Sham(ألشَّام)
and that was after the Hajj(حَجْ) of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
in which Al-Khalifah(خليفه) reprimanded Khalid(خالد) for it, and told him never do that again.
And then he told him because no one will relieve the distress of the Muslims like you
and no one will crack the enemy and break them like you.
So don't do something like that again.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) receives this letter and he feels the urgency of the situation.
He must get to Ash-Sham(ألشَّام) immediately,
because these four Roman armies are descending on the Muslims as fast as they can.
And if he doesn't make it in time, it will be too late. But the problem is
all of the routes that connect Al-Iraq(ألعراق) to Ash-Sham(ألشَّام) are lined up by Roman Garrisons.
So if he is going to take those traditional routes, he must fight with these Garrison's
and that will hold him back and delay his assistance to the Muslims in Ash-Sham(ألشَّام).
And he needs to get there immediately. So he gathered all of his guides,
the guides in the desert because Yani(يعني) the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم don’t know this territory,
so they have guides, local people, he gathered them all he told them,
This is what I need to do! I need to go behind all of the Roman lines.
And I need to dig deep into Ash-Sham(ألشَّام) without meeting any resistance.
They told him: There's no way to do that.
These are the traditional routes.
This is all what we can offer you, he said: You have to do me something!
Find me another way.
They said: There isn't another way
because the only other way which is crossing the desert
is a path that was never ever crossed before by an army
and it's a path that even if a lone traveler takes, he still fears on his life.
You know sometimes a lone traveler can make it
but it's only the best of them and it's very risky
but for entire army loaded with weapons and equipment
it's an impossible feat and nobody has ever done it before.
The Romans have been here for centuries and they never did it.
The Persians have been in this land for some time they never did it, nobody did it before.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) said: That's the only way tell me how to do it.?
None of the guides was willing to bear that responsibility.
They said: It will be a disaster for the Muslims, Mahlakah(محلكة).
The Muslims will perish, except for one of the guides, Rafiya Bin Umair(رافع بن عمير).
He said: I could help you with that.
Now the Muslims were discussing this with Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد),
it is a major feat it couldn't be a disaster on the entire army.
Half of the forces in Iraq could perish in the desert.
The guides have given Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) their opinion.
They told him: You can't do it.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) responded by saying;
ان المسلم ينبغي اَلَا يكترس بشيء يقى فيه مع ماعونت الله له
He said: The Muslim should not care about anything, he does.
If he has the assistance of Allah on his side.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) was willing to take the risk.
He was audacious and such an enterprising person, he was willing to take this risk
and is telling the guides and the army that we should not bother, we should not care at all about anything,
if Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ is with us.
Tell me what we could do, and we'll do it.
Rafiya Bin Umair(رافع بن عمير) stands up and said: O Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد),
if you insist on us doing that, this is what we have to do.
I want you to give me the strongest 20 camels that you have in the army.
So he handed them over, he deprived them from water
and then when they were very thirsty, he gave them a lot of water to drink.
And then he cut off their lips, mask the mouth and also prevented them from urinating
and he made sure that every soldier in the Army has transportation,
and he told them to load up five days worth of water Bismillah( بسم الله) let's start.
And they started from Qaraqir(قراقر) and their destination was Suwaa(سوَّى).
Five days travel without any source of water and without any settlements along the way.
It is a very rough terrain, desert no one lives there
five days you're not gonna see anyone if you make it, from Qaraqir(قراقر) to Suwaa(سوَّى).
Then after that there are settlements that you could survive on.
But you have to make this segment which is five days long,
without any supplements whatsoever.
They started the journey Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
planned it in a way that they would travel double the distance
by traveling at night and traveling in the morning.
You have to put more effort in it.
And they went through this rough terrain this desert,
under the guidance of Rafiya Bin Umair(رافع بن عمير).
After five days, they ran out of their water those 20 camels that were packed with water,
they would slaughter them and empty the stomach contents and give it to the horses,
so the horses would drink from what's in the inside of the camels
and then the soldiers would drink from their supplies of water.
After five days Rafiya(رافع) has told them, you will find sources of water there will be some water.
But he couldn't see it, because he got this disease in his eyes, which temporarily blinded him.
So now, five days are over, we don't have any water left.
Tell us where the water is.
The guide cannot see.
They tell him: Come on, you have to do something for us.
He said: Alright, look for this particular tree.
And he told them that particular species.
They went looking for it they couldn't find it. He said: Look for it.
Again, they went to look but then they found it but the tree was already chopped.
So they found the trunk of it.
He said: Dig next to the tree.
And when they were digging, they came to some spring of water.
He told them: I've never been here except once and that was with my father 30 years ago.
So he remembered the tree and remembered that there was water there
but he has never been there for over 30 years and he said:
He refreshed in his mind remembered where the water would be
even though he was temporarily blind,
that it could have been because of the Sun in the desert sometimes
it cause you to lose your sight because of the reflection of light
on the sand if it's bright in color.
So they reached and there was a some poetry made about that,
لِلَّهِ دَرُّ رافِعٍ أَنّى اِهتَدى
فَوَّزَ مِن قَراقِرٍ إِلى سُوى
خِمْسًا إِذَا سَارَ بِهِ الْجِبْسُ بَكَى
ما سَارها من قبله إنسٌ يُرى
May Allah reward Rafiya(رافع), How was he guided
to travel from Qaraqir(قراقر) all the way to Suwaa(سوى),
five days if any army marches through it, it would cry.
No one ever marched there before you.
So this was the first time ever this happened.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) is now in the depth of Ash-Sham(ألشَّام).
It was a surprise for the Romans.
How could he make it with such speed?
How could he make it unnoticed what happened to all of our Garrison's on the way
the Romans have been there for centuries.
They know what the traditional routes are, they are all protected.
And now suddenly they find Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) with his army in their midst,
and they already have heard about the reputation of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد).
So for them, this was a miracle.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) whom they've been hearing about all of these stories
and now their stories were confirmed.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) landed out of nowhere in the middle of our land,
with such speed and unnoticed.
And that struck fear in their hearts.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) gets into Ash-Sham(ألشَّام)
and he is now ready to reinforce the Muslims.
The plan was, we should not fight them separately, four armies are easier to take on than one.
So he told the Muslim armies to join together.
He said: When your numbers are small don't fight the enemy separately.
Bring your numbers together.
So the three armies were told to withdraw from all of the territory that they occupied.
Leave Damascus! Leave Hims(حمص)! Just come back all the way to Yarmook(يرموك),
which is in present day Jordan.
So that will be the battlefield where they would meet the army of the Romans.
Three armies succeeded in withdrawing the army Yazeed(يزيد), the army of Sharhabil(شرحبيل)
and the army of Abu Obaidah(أبوعبيدة).
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) got bogged down in Falastine(فلسطين)
because the distance between him and the Roman army was so short,
he cannot turn away his back without being hit from the rear.
So he had to maneuver slowly and slowly.
So Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) had two choices,
either to tell Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) to withdraw and suffer the consequences
or he goes in and joins hands with Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص)
and they give the Roman army a shot, which was 90,000 Strong.
Khalid(خالد) went with the latter, so he rushed into Falastine(فلسطين)
joined hands with Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) and they fought the battle of Ajnadeen(أجنادين),
which was a great victory for the Muslims and a disaster to the Romans.
The news reached to Heracles, he said: This is the beginning of our defeat.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) and Amr(عمر) they withdrew to Al-Yarmook(أليرموك).
Now Heracul(هراقل) is already sensing the danger.
And he knows that his soldiers are gonna have a hard time standing up against the Muslims.
So what he told his generals he said;
Choose a battleground that is very wide from the front, but is very narrow from the back
in order to refuse our soldiers the option of retreating.
He saw that this is the only way to deal with these Muslims.
Our soldiers cannot stand in front of them.
So they chose Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), they chose a position of Yarmook(يرموك)
in front of them was an open plan and behind them was a cliff.
So obviously, you can't run away, a cliff is behind you.
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) as soon as he saw that, he said;
أبشرو قد جَآء نصر فولله قلَّى ما يعتي محصورٌ بخير
He said; Rejoice.
Look at the positiveness of the Sahabah(صحابه) they would make a good news out of anything.
Rejoice! Victory is on its way
because they have cornered themselves and rarely does a cornered man ever survive.
You've cornered yourself, you chose to put yourself in that position.
Rarely has anybody who has done that come out with any good.
The enemy was 250,000, While the Muslims when they joined together were 40,000
and that is a Battle of Al-Yarmook(أليرموك)
which we will talk about in sha Allah Ta'ala(إنشاء الله تعالى) Monday.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ